so this is a a quote
from a arjun animal terror
you might name you said
you said
keep a watchful eye on the gateway
not acting out of pressure that endures
on any level
regardless of how long it endures
[Music] this is what will make you an island for
this is what will make you an island for
yourself
and make you an island for yourself
in regard to everything and everyone you
will experience until the aggregates
break apart so
so
just to recap
to go through it again what is the
gateway that one must be guarding correctly correctly
established mindfulness
on that peripheral level
for which
virtue and sense restraint unnecessary
prerequisites as we said in previous talks you won't
as we said in previous talks you won't
even
see you won't even know how to see it will
you won't even know how to see it will
not appear for you
the you know the domain of the peripheral
you know the domain of the peripheral
unless your behavior has been purified
beforehand unless you have been
cultivating virtue and sense restraint
and watchfulness and being moderate in
eating and so on
then when you
when you try to apply this like okay
i'll learn how to
well i'll learn how to recognize what's
also there in my experience right here
right now such as this body for example
without needing to look at it
to know that it's there because you
already know that it's there otherwise
how would you know what to look for
but it's their dependence on that
direct seeing as a measure of existence
and putting that peripheral knowledge of
what's already there existing second
so it's learning how to reverse that
order fix it up
you do that you guard that that's the
gateway that's right order right mindfulness
that's right order right mindfulness
so that yeah okay so you're guiding that
right order
because in a way that you're set at the
gate the gateway
is that mental choosing
to engage
with unwholesome
things again yeah perspective
again yeah perspective
for your choice
is the perspective of the right order
so
right order is the gateway so
you choose whether to to pervert the
order and give into the pressure
and you know
put the second is first so for example
you might follow the body correctly on
the peripheral level as the gateway your
virtue has been
cultivated beforehand and so on and now
you have you know some doubts about some
things regarding the body regarding this but
regarding the body regarding this but
all of that all of those doubts mental
states hindrances pressures
are within the body enduring there on
the peripheral level so there is never a
reason to abandon that and put it second
and prioritize that which doubt
presented you with
so it's choosing to abandon the gateway
when you choose to accept what doubt
presented you with
you walk away from it and that's the
whole point of doubt as a hindrance
it's the whole the whole trick of it is
just to get you to walk away from your
post
that's why you can never
that's what the right answers will never
satisfy that doubt because there was
never a point there was just a pretext
but unless you're able to withstand the
pressure of the doubt
and sustain the right ordering face of
it you will not be able to um to endure
it
so you see whatever hinges will arise
it all arises
within exactly
exactly
hindrance tries to throw you throw you
off pressure you pull you scare you
pressure you pull you scare you
frighten you all these things just so
you abandon the post of the right order
just so you drop
or obscure or walk away from the
recognition of peripherally enduring
body affair
so yeah
it makes you engage with
it it's not making you engaged
it's pressuring you too do you choose to
yeah that's why you are responsible for
the uh
if hindrances hinder you you're not
responsible for hindrances arising
but you're responsible if you're
hindered by them because means like oh
you accepted the order that they were
pressuring you for
you acted out of them in other words
so you see that order correct
you endure the order in face of the
pressure of the hindrances that's it
and that's how you go surround the
hindrances surmounting the hindrances
not resolving them not finding the right
answers for them but isn't it also you
know you see a hindrance
there pressure in you
but you cannot see that that
you can choose to engage with it you can
choose to give in yeah
but then you see the power of your
choice the power you have there
the power you have there
yeah you can either give in or or not
yeah but that power of your choice it's
not rooted just in like
the the you or something
it's rooted in the options sure but that
option says yeah so the option is to
stay the gateway
and not prioritize the hindrance or to
prioritize the hindrance
and uh so what's really the power there
it's not the choice it's the knowledge
behind it sure the choice is the power
exactly knowledge what to do
right if you don't know you must stay at
the gateway despite all the pressure
despite all the unnatural feeling of it
because it feels just much more
natural and satisfying to address this
and fix it and sort it this pressure
that or the doubt or whatever else but
unless you have thoroughly understood
that no that's a trap
you won't do it so you can't
accidentally or spontaneously choose to
guard the right order and become a sort
of partner that's impossible
you need to understand the value it's
through through like pondering on it
beforehand and then stick to it and
endure it against the grain against the
pull
no matter what the world's telling you
you know exactly
well whatever is telling you you have a
reference point now so if what the
world's telling you is according to the
right order you say okay the world is
right in this instance if the world is
telling you the opposite side or the
world is wrong in this distance and that's
and that's
so that's again
guarding you say you're saying
guiding that gateway
is not letting those hindrances
in not engaging with them
yeah it's really not engaging with them
not engaging because
letting them in might be misconstrued
i know what you mean
i know what i meant probably if i said
it before but
hearing it now it it
it might be miscontrolled like oh i must
prevent them from coming to me
no their eyes they come to the doorstep
you just don't let them in how do you
let them in well you welcome them you
delight in them you accept them
so you don't do that
but at the same time as i said so many
times before
you don't trust you don't try to chase
them away either because they would also
require you to abandon your post at the
very threshold of your of the gateway
you need to go out and start chasing
them and so on which means you know you
turn your back to that which you should
have guarded um um
okay
so endure the endure the pressure
to let them in if if they're agreeable
and endure the poll to chase them away
if they're disagreeable
and enjoy the pull to ignore them if
they're neither
to to sort of become careless and
indolent in regard to they're going to
sleep with the person yeah because look
they're not trying to come in oh i can
snooze at the post exactly yeah no
they're not trying to come in great so
i'm not i don't have to endure the
the pull of chasing them away and the
pressure of trying to of them trying to
get in but i certainly should not go to
sleep either
so it's it's relaxing when they're not
trying to get in and they're just
sitting there
but at the same time i shouldn't be too
relaxed and and that's why that's the
subtlest the neutral feeling that
basically needs to be
uh understood because it's just so easy
to to become indolent and uh careless
about complacent distracted from yeah
complacent distracted from yeah
so vigilant in times of
calm yeah yeah vengeance in times of
calm and then
and then
persistent in in in every other time so
if it's the
uh pressure to welcome it you persist in
not doing so
if it's the pull to take you pull you
out to chase them away if they're un
if they're disagreeable
you also have to persist in that and
during that pool
so this this is a quick a strange
question about how not to choose
to engage with those pressures of
craving pleasure how do you
well no see that that's a wrong question
because it already implies that you
start engaged you don't
you start pressured
or pulled
but that's not the engagement
the engagement is what you do on account
of that pressure that you feel
the disagreeability of the pressure
basically that you feel the only way not
to do that
is to not take out that feeling and
develop sufficient mindfulness in regard
to it peripherally and endure it
great and also see the value in doing
that well yeah that needs to come
beforehand you can't start doing this
without still doubting the value of
doing it
so this kind of question comes up a lot
because well it comes up a lot because
people want to jump the queue
people understand this people are
pressured by the pain but they want the
answer to get rid of the pain which
means they keep doing the same thing
acting out of pain
but the gradual training is there
repeated so many times in the sutures
and in our talks
so
virtue is the first
guarding of the sense doors sense
restraint moderation
do that all the doubt that comes well
restrain it
that's the point
it's not the point to find the
satisfying answer over and over and over
again the point is to endure the
non-answering on the basis of your
virtue and mindfulness
otherwise you just give in you build
this up you're coming near the gateway
and then you just run out chasing the
answers and so on and forget where you
should have stopped
and protected it
so that's why it keeps coming up because
people are impatient
you always want someone to tell you
what you must do yeah
but they tell you what to do
so and then you want to be told again
what you need to do because
the the the satisfaction of the answer
has run out and the principle of acting
out of pressure of the pull hasn't
diminished hasn't changed you still act
out you haven't practiced that yet you
you haven't practiced that yet you
haven't practiced that yeah you all
you've been doing is acting out and
finding answers which you have to start
with but the point is the point comes
when you have sufficient amount of
answers you have sufficient amount of
information now you need to start
applying it and enduring that doubt
that's going to become more and more
irrational the more you don't give in to
it
and then he's going to be more and more
pressuring so to speak but you have the
virtue you have the sense restraint got it and
you have the sense restraint got it and
you endured it and it will have to come
down the mind will have to calm down
unless you throw your bone again and
and
as i was reading about the development
of the perception of abandoning that
that kind of perception must be
dividend and it's
and it's
pretty much similar what what you're
saying here
i'll just read it and which is the
perception of abandoning
here and under a bighu does not give
into a risen thoughts or sense design
he abandons them removes them gets rid
of them makes them disappear yeah he
does not give him to arisen thoughts of
your will he abandons him
he does not give in to arisen thoughts
of harming he abandons them he does not
give into the continual arising of evil
unwholesome things yeah he advanced him
this is called the perception of exactly
so and that's often see
people read just that and mean like oh i
must prevent these things from arising
so i must get rid of them so these
thoughts come and i must have them not
come and the result of it is you abandon the
and the result of it is you abandon the
gateway you abandon the mindfulness you
abandon the right order and you welcome
and you engage and you start fighting or
chasing or whatever else these thoughts
which is what they wanted you to do they
wanted you to abandon the gateway and
accept them so to try to abandon
thoughts you actually accepted them and
abandoned that which you shouldn't have
abandoned which is the right order of
your right mindfulness
so yes you can understand abandonment to
mean that
but you can also understand abandonment
to mean what we are saying it means
so you abandon the thoughts you abandon
these wild animals they will stop coming
to you if you stop feeding them
because it's endless if you start
chasing them and killing them one by one
they keep popping back up
new ones so you you can't
you know you can cancel the thought and
what will is that now you're free from
thoughts forever you're free from
underlying currency of like the
pressuring feeling in regard no nothing
has changed you just got rid of the
specific thought that bothered you
so yeah that's a form of abandonment but
obviously where does that lead
but if you do the embandment or if you
understand the abandonment the way i'm
describing it then you realize okay so
you you actually unplug uproot remove
that fuel for these thoughts to come
back so oh yeah you abandoned them
and not just one instance of it but now
they stop coming you're no longer
feeding them exactly because you stop
feeding them so yes by not welcoming you
will abandon them and that's how monks
can fully abandon these thoughts and
the unskillful states
but particularly this last point he does
not give into the continual arising of
evil so yeah because he'll stop coming
exactly and they are continually they're
continually arising he's not giving in
the order is not
uh
compromised the right order the
mindfulness established on the you know
body peripherally correctly
that gateway is not abandoned doesn't
matter how continually these thoughts
arise this does not change
this does not change
so the other hand
the one who practices is steadfast in
that and
and
it basically it becomes fortified in
that right order the the more that's
developed the less and less
the less and less
the
these thoughts would be coming so to
speak there will be fewer and fewer and
fewer and the pressure would be fading
away because each time you abandon the
gateway you engage with the thorns which means
you engage with the thorns which means
that's what they feed on they see they
can move you they'll keep coming to try
and move you
but if after a sufficient amount of time
the order hasn't moved
they will basically drift away lose
interest and walk away see that they've
been wasting their time
but in in in this or this last thing
that he doesn't give in to the continual
he doesn't give in to the continual
rising
is saying
you know that's when you start doing
this abandoning abandoning evil thought
comes up every now and then
last and then there's one that can also
be this long one last push so to speak
from uh
mara if you could say
this they give he gives one last try you know
they give he gives one last try you know
to really get you know you know lots of
lustful thoughts and start arising just
once continuously right right right
right and it's in a way well that's
exactly what happens yeah if you're
still engaging with thoughts
individually know trying to chase them away get rid
know trying to chase them away get rid
of them when it's one or two you do it
successfully yeah so then exactly three
or four you can't keep up 15 16 oh
you're done if that was the only way of
abandonment that you knew
getting together you'll get rid of
you'll be overwhelmed overwhelmed
quickly so yeah that might work for one
thought exactly and that's exactly why
people people struggle because it kind
of works initially and they think oh so
that's the abandonment they might do but
they don't realize that abandonment that
you must do is basically on the level of
fortifying where you stand
not fighting more and more thoughts at
the same time because that's impossible
that's going to run out that's basically
exhausting and you'll be going to be run
over you won't be fortified to that no matter
you won't be fortified to that no matter
what
so if there is one thought and you can
just ignore it or downhole some kind
sure abandon it in that way but don't
don't confuse that for the uprooting of
it like you know i don't want to think
about this yeah that's fine if it works
but the time will come when they will
not work and if there's the only way of
abandoning between you
you're going to be overrun they'll be
inside you'll be running out the cable
is gone destroyed
you know precepts compromise and
everything else
so
you have to people have to basically
broaden the understanding of what
abandonment is and certainly stop
conflating it with i must stop thinking
and get rid of this because even the
thought of abandoning this particular
thought is another thought
so thinking that you must stop thinking
it's not
abandonment at all and it's actually a
contradiction in terms which means as
such it's quite the wrong view and often
you see that in
buddhist meditations and traditions so
far just stop thinking stop thinking
focus now feel about all of these
focusing and feeling and stuff our
thoughts are perceptions yet here you
are believing you could stop your
thoughts
so you not just that that's not the
abandonment you're actually kind of not
even seeing the nature of that which is
it in front of your gate
you're completely confused about it
you think it's not real you think it's
not there these thoughts are gone my
mind is empty of thoughts which is
another thought
now you need to see the thoughts that
always being there
and the only way you can do is protect
the gateway in regard to it and
and
even if there's
there are no thoughts evil
unwholesome thoughts
you're still
developing on keeping that uh
perception of a ban abandoning
there yeah and what would that
keeping be
you would be sustaining of the order
that's exactly what it is as i said
before sustaining of the right order
peripheral mindfulness of the body being
there means everything else that you're
means everything else that you're
experiencing within that is going to be
experienced in a detached manner
as i'm going to say whatever feeling he
feels he feels it detached
that's that's exactly what it is you
protect that that's the abandonment of
any attachment
abandonment or any any any base for
passion so sustain it
until the the
diversion delusion and try any traces of
it to completely evaporate and that's it
it's quite a nice nice practice and you
know it's not that confusing red it's
not that confusing obviously but exactly
that's the point because it is the right
practice the closer you get to it the more will
the closer you get to it the more will
your mind try to throw from it that's
what maori is and your own mind is the
you know
an assassin that pretends to be a friend
as the suitors say
so
the more you start doing it rightly the
stronger the doubts will be
which means the more of the fortifying
of the right order you have to do and
sustain the more faith you
the faith is kind of pretty accurate
isn't it
and that's you know you could
see that perception
you have that in the back of your mind
abandoning all i need to do is abandon
all i need to do is abandon
those unwholesome things i don't have to
choose them i don't have to engage with
those things
so how do you abandon them oh so i don't
have to do anything really
i don't have to go out of my way to
abandon them i just have to
stay here and not go anywhere basically
and they will be
abandoned or not being given attention
to and acted out of and welcomed and
delighted engaged and so on encouraged
encouraged not invited not invited all of that
not invited not invited all of that
and
yeah that's that's difficult to do you
know obviously because yeah because
that's basically
now on the level of
uh enduring it mentally that discomfort
of that you know waiting waiting
patience in front of you like trying to
pressure you trying to to to convince
you or do this to that let them in go out or
or do this to that let them in go out or
just one slip you get careless oh oh
where oh that's it that's it you act it
out so yeah that's that's the pain all
the practice but pain of the development
but if you take it on
that's also the pain that results in
uprooting of any basis for pain in the
future so it's not just managing anymore
so it's not just managing anymore
which was always before the thought
comes you chase it away ah see now i'm
free and then another thought comes
and then another thought comes
oh so i have to chase it away again
which means i'm not really free i'm
pressured by the duty of having to chase
you away having to deal with it
and then too many thoughts come and you
can't deal with it
because you only knew how to deal with
individual thoughts by kind of
addressing them changing them chasing
them away
so management will never result in
freedom only in postponing the obvious
only in postponing the obvious
that you were still equally pressured
and as you said as i said i could
it is what will make you an island for
yourself yeah exactly
consistent vigilance completely
basically self-sufficient internally contained
self-sufficient internally contained
detached
islands detached from any other but from
the from the beginning it's the same
practice all the way it's just yeah yeah
yeah yeah same principle
just needs to be fortified and developed
further and further and further
before to find the same principle yep
and it's exactly the the gist of every
gradual training that it would have
described which is always the same
creative training but every instance of
this curve it's always the same
the same principle
take it on do this do this to this and
then dwell in these states and protect
these states and so on and there's only
one outcome you'll be in ireland to
yourself